<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://versteeg-ou.github.io/coll-data-site/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://versteeg-ou.github.io/coll-data-site/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-13T16:52:08-04:00</updated><id>https://versteeg-ou.github.io/coll-data-site/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ohio University Libraries Collections-as-data Prototype</title><subtitle>Explore Ohio University Libraries collections-as-data on this prototype site.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">About this prototype</title><link href="https://versteeg-ou.github.io/coll-data-site/about/update/2021/10/08/about-this-prototype.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About this prototype" /><published>2021-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://versteeg-ou.github.io/coll-data-site/about/update/2021/10/08/about-this-prototype</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://versteeg-ou.github.io/coll-data-site/about/update/2021/10/08/about-this-prototype.html">&lt;p&gt;This prototype web site is intended to demo Jekyll as a way to publish Ohio University Libraries  &lt;a href=&quot;https://collectionsasdata.github.io/statement/&quot;&gt;collections-as-data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is a static site generator that is also built in to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, making it easy to deploy on their free web hosting for open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar collections-as-data sites from other Universities include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cadatpitt.github.io/&quot;&gt;Collections as Data at Pitt&lt;/a&gt;, which uses Jekyll and github.io as documentation for a GitHub repository.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://data.nls.uk/&quot;&gt;Data Foundry&lt;/a&gt; from the National Library of Scotland, which uses WordPress as a front end for Amazon S3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other library collections-as-data projects currently exist only as a GitHub repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/marriott-library/collections-as-data&quot;&gt;Marriott Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a static site generator like Jekyll enables significant integration, automation, and customization, but requires some skill and configuration to deploy. There are dozens of static site generators with a variety of pros and cons, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sphinx-doc.org/&quot;&gt;Sphinx&lt;/a&gt; which is popular for documentation in the Python community and works with &lt;a href=&quot;https://readthedocs.org/&quot;&gt;Read the Docs&lt;/a&gt;, another host for open source documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LibStatic &lt;a href=&quot;https://lib-static.github.io/&quot;&gt;methodology statement&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Idaho makes the case for using Jekyll and the JAM stack for library projects. They use Jekyll as the engine for their &lt;a href=&quot;https://collectionbuilder.github.io/&quot;&gt;CollectionBuilder&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/uidaholib/oral-history-as-data&quot;&gt;Oral History as Data&lt;/a&gt; projects. Tech-for-humanists tutorials site &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/&quot;&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt; offers a tutorial on &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;building a static website with Jekyll and GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt; which they recommend if you want an “entirely free, easy-to-maintain, preservation-friendly, secure website over which you have full control”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="about" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">This prototype web site is intended to demo Jekyll as a way to publish Ohio University Libraries collections-as-data. Jekyll is a static site generator that is also built in to GitHub, making it easy to deploy on their free web hosting for open source projects.</summary></entry></feed>